Preliminary Inventory to the Louis Edgar Browne Papers, 1917-1956
Hoover Institution Archives
Louis Edgar Browne Papers,
1917-1956
69033
Browne, Louis Edgar, 1891-1951
2 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 2 envelopes (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Dispatches, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to political conditions in Russia during the Russian Revolution, Allied intervention in Russia, and political conditions in Turkey at the end of World War I. Entire collection also available on microfilm (1 reel).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
World War, 1914-1918; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Turkey; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920; Turkey--History--Revolution, 1918-1923; Journalists
Container List
- Trade: Milliye nos. 1-2, 1919 September 14 and 17 (Box 1., Folder 1)
- Umumi Kongre Heyeti, Umumi Kongre Beyannamesi, Sivas, 1335 September 11 (Folder 2)
- Dispatch concerning Halidé Edib, no. 1, n.d. (in English) (Folder 3a)
- Miscellaneous papers concerning the Sivas Congress. Includes conversations with Charles R. Crane, chief member of the American section of the Allied Committee on Mandates for Turkey (in English) (Folder 3b)
- Sharki Anadolu mudafan-i hukuh cemiyeti. Sharki Anadolu Vilayeti Erzerum kangresi beyannamesi, 1335 August 7 (Folder 3c)
- United States Naval Radio Press, 1919 August 11, 28 and 31, September 15. USS Galveston,1919 August 31 (Folder 3d)
- Telegraphic dispatches, in draft form, from Sivas, 1919 September (in English) (Folder 3e)
- Letter to Charles R. Crane, 1919 August 25 (Folder 3f)
- United States Navy reports on the Greek occupation of Smyrna, 1919 May (Folder 3g)
- National Congress of Sivas to the President of the Senate of the United States of America, 1919 September 19 (Folder 3h)
- Umumi Knogre Heyeti, Umumi Kongre Beyannamesi. Sivas, 1335 September 11 (Folder 3i)
- Edib, Halidé. Letters to the American public, Istanbul, 1919 August 17 (Folder 3j)
- Dispatches. Typed drafts, carbons (Folder 3k)
- Miscellaneous material on National Congress at Sivas. Memoranda, notes, inauguration speech of Kemal Pacha, miscellaneous translations, and manuscripts (Folder 3l)
- "Copie du Memorandum remis le Janvier 18, 1919 aux Hauts Commissaires des Puissances Alliées et au Commissaire des Etats-Unis d'Amerique," Constantinople, 1919 (Folder 4)
- Correspondence
  - Corey, Herbert, 1919 October, 1920 May (Folder 5)
  - Bristol, Rear Admiral Mark, 1919 October 24, December 6 (Folder 6)
  - Campbell, W. Archie, 1919 October 18, 1921 February 7, 1922 September 16 (Folder 7)
  - Carter, John, Jr., 1919 December 5, 9 1920 March 8 (Folder 8)
- Diary, 1919 (Folder 9)
- The Georgian Messenger, nos. 1-8, 1919 February 23 -April 26 (in English) (Folder 10)
- The Trans-Caucasian Post, nos. 1-17, 1919 February 21 -April 26 (in English) (Folder 11)
- Photographs (Folder 12)
- Covenant Preamble, Paris, 1919 February 14 (Folder 13)
- Dispatches to Chicago Daily News, nos. 39-54, 1919 October 1-November 1 (Folder 14)
- Dispatches from Turkey, n.d. (Folder 15)
- Copy of a section of The Nineteenth Century, vol. LXXIX, no. 472, "The Future of Asiatic Turkey" (Folder 16)
- Why Armenia Should Be Free, by Dr. G. Dasdermadjian, Boston, Hairenik Publishing Co., 1919 (Folder 17)
- Address by President Wilson, delivered at Mt. Vernon, 1918 July 4 (Folder 18)
- Address by President Wilson, delivered at Joint Session of Congress, 1918 November 11 (Folder 19)
- Correspondence with J. C. Callahan, 1919 October 17, December 9 (Folder 20)
- "Turkish Conscription." Graph, 1914 (Folder 21a)
- "Nationalities in Turkey." Map and Table (Folder 21b)
- Population statistics before 1914 (Folder 21c)
- Population statistics for 1893-1897 (Folder 21d)
- Public schools in Turkey, n.d. (Folder 21e)
- Dispatches from Greece, September 1-10 (Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous newspaper clippings regarding Kemal, etc. (in French) (Folder 23)
- Correspondence with A. Lapine, 1919 December 8, 1920 February 11, March 17 (Folder 24)
- Letter from the National Congress at Sivas to the President of the Senate of the United States, signed by Mustaysha Kemal Pacha and four other officials, 1919 September 9 (Folder 25)
- Extract of telegram sent by the National Congress at Sivas to "Your Majesty," 1919 September 1 (Folder 26)
- Description of events at National Congress at Sivas. Typescript with some handwritten variations (Folder 27)
- Excerpts from Isvestia, Rabochy Narod, Petrograd Ryech, Vpered, Vetser, etc. (in English), and unidentified excerpts, regarding the statements by Trotsky, 1917 November 22, 28; recognition of Bolshevik government by the United States; decree on nationalization of banks; Brest Litovsk; Red Cross 'conspiracy' (Box 2., Folder 1.)
- Dispatches on Russian affairs, 1917 October-1918 May (Folder 2)
- Mimeographed sheets entitled "Opinion" on political affairs in Russia, etc. (in French) (Folder 3)
- Newspaper clippings regarding Russian conditions, Germany, etc. (in English) (Folder 4)
- Typescript report entitled "Russian American Commercial Relations," written after 1916. Includes miscellaneous notes on Trotsky (Folder 5)
- Translation of Pravda, regarding arrival of German Ambassador, 1918 April 24 (Folder 6a)
- Copy of Union of Soviet Socialist Republics appeal to the United States regarding chief of American Red Cross, Raymond Robins, n.d. (Folder 6b)
- Memorandum on various subjects, including Vladivostok, the Murmansk incidents, and foreign relations, 1918 April (Folder 6c)
- Table of governments in Russia, 1917 March-October (Folder 6d)
- "Russian Revolutionary Pamphlets, Decrees, Orders and Proclamations of the Provisional Workmen's and Peasants' Government of the Russian Republic," vol. 1, 1917 October 25 -December 1. Petrograd, 1918 February. Typescript (Folder 6e)
- Material regarding French forces leaving Odessa, 1919 April? (Folder 6f)
- Memorandum entitled 'Vechnie Chass', April 4; typescript entitled "Evacuation of French Expeditionary Force and Russian Volunteer Guards from Odessa," 1919 April 4; excerpt from News ( Isvestia)' "Comrade Workmen of the City of Sebastopol" (Folder 6g)
- Memorandum from William B. Webster(?) on Bolshevism in Russia, Stockholm, 1918 October 12 (Folder 6h)
- Reports by A. Lessin, "Germans in the Baltic Provinces" (Folder 6i)
- Note quoting Lenin, March 14 (Folder 6j)
- Dispatch, Petrograd, January 13. Typescript (Folder 6k)
- 6l Memoranda entitled "Pro and Con for Allied Recognition of the Soviet Form of Government," 1918 May 2 and 5
- "Lenin and His Party." notes based on Tsialovski's 'Bolsheviki' regarding Bolsheviks found in the political section of the police department in Moscow, and Baturin's 'History of Social Democracy in Russia.' Typescript (Folder 7)
- Report on Russo-Ukraine conflict. Typescript (Folder 8)
- Report on law in Russia, 1918 August (Folder 9)
- Report on German forces in Ukraine. Typescript with handwritten annotations (Folder 10)
- Report on Japanese intervention in Russia (and Siberia, etc.) (Folder 11)
- Report on Czechoslovak forces in Russia, 1918 July. Typescript with handwritten annotations (Folder 12)
- Report on Finnish socialists and the effects on Russia. Typescript with handwritten annotations (Folder 13)
- One package of negative photostats from the Chicago Daily News, of articles on the Russian situation, mostly by LEB (Box 3.)